Guide to the John and Ann Garvey Papers AIA.088
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John and Ann Garvey Papers
1935-2020
1980-2019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Garvey, John
Garvey, Ann
AIA.088
18.5 linear feet in 33 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, and 2 oversize folders in shared housing
1 audiocassette
Ann and her late husband John Garvey were educators and active members of the New York City Irish American community. The couple were past presidents and founding members of the American Irish Teachers Association (AITA), and focused much of their organizing on educational initiatives to increase and improve the teaching of Irish and Irish American culture and history. The John and Ann Garvey Papers (dated 1935-2019) document the Garveys teaching through organizational newsletters (the majority of which are from the AITA), and conference programs, as well as agendas, meeting notes, and correspondence from various committee meetings. The collection also documents the Garveys engagement with Irish American organizations through photographs, newspaper articles, and programs for conventions and other annual events. Organizations such as the Ancient Order of Hibernians, the United Irish Counties Association of New York, and various County Mayo-centered social organizations (especially the Mayo Society of New York) are particularly well represented.
Scope and Contents
The John and Ann Garvey Papers (dated 1935-2020) consist of materials documenting the couple's work as educators and their engagement with numerous Irish American organizations in the Greater New York City area. Materials documenting the Garveys teaching include organizational newsletters (the majority of which are from the American Irish Teachers Association), and conference programs, as well as agendas, meeting notes, and correspondence from various committee meetings. These materials focus almost exclusively on organizations and education initiatives devoted to increasing and improving the teaching Irish and Irish American culture and history, such as a proposed curriculum on the Irish Famine/Great Hunger. The collection also documents the Garveys engagement with Irish American organizations through photographs, newspaper articles, and programs for conventions and other annual events. Organizations like the Ancient Order of Hibernians, the United Irish Counties Association of New York, and various County Mayo-centered social organizations (especially the Mayo Society of New York) are particularly well represented.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series: Series I. Education; Series II. County Mayo; Series III. Irish American Organizations; and Series IV. 2021 Accretion. Folders arranged alphabetically, with the exception of Series IV, which has not been arranged by an archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ann Garvey in March 2020, with a further accretion donated in October 2021; the accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2020.024 and 2021.063.
Appraisal
The repository kept three "Ceart Vótála" buttons; duplicates beyond this amount were returned to the donor. One t-shirt advocating the initiative to include the Irish Famine/Great Hunger in New York State's human rights curriculum was also appraised out of the collection.
Publications, photocopies of newspaper clippings, and duplicate event programs from the 2021 accretion were appraised out of the collection upon its arrival.
Biographical Note for John Garvey
John J. Garvey (d. 2018) was an Irish American educator who held numerous leadership positions in the Irish American community. Garvey worked the bulk of his professional career in the New York City public school system, with over three decades at P.S. 85. He focused much of his attention on educational outreach programs for new immigrants, as well as improving the treatment of Irish and Irish American history in curriculum. A native of County Mayo, Garvey studied at St. Muredach's College in Ballina (County Mayo) and Patrician College in Ballyfin (County Laois), later earning a B.A. from Fordham University in Marketing and Management, and and M.A. in Distributive Education from NYU.
Garvey was a president and founding member of the Irish American Teachers Association, a historian and president of the Mayo Society of New York, a member of the Board of Directors for the Emerald Isle Immigration Center, and a chair of the Irish American Heritage and Culture Committee (New York City Board of Education). He was also an essay judge for the St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee essay competition, a member of the Ancient Order of Hibernians (Division 4), and a member of the Bronx Gaelic League.
Source:
Emerald Isle Immigration Center. "In Memory of John J. Garvey." https://eiic.org/blog/in-memory-of-john-j-garvey/ (retrieved September 11, 2020).
Biographical Note for Ann Garvey
Ann Garvey is an Irish American educator who has held numerous leadership positions in the Irish American community. She has held positions as a lecturer at NYU's Graduate School of Education and as an Educational Evaluator with the New York City Board of Education. Garvey is the past president of the American Irish Teachers Association (AITA), during which time she led the organization's campaign to include curriculum on Ireland's Great Hunger (commonly referred to as Ireland's Famine) in New York State's Human Rights Curriculum law, mandating study of this historical moment throughout the state. Alongside her husband John, Ann organized campaigns for the United States Postal Service to issue a commemorative stamp for the Great Hunger. In 1998, Ann was named Irish Woman of the Year by the Irish American Heritage and Culture Committee (New York City Board of Education) for her contributions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Irish Americans.; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans -- History.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Teachers; Ireland -- History -- Famine, 1845-1852; Ireland -- History -- Study and teaching; Garvey, Ann; Mayo Society of New York; Ancient Order of Hibernians; United Irish Counties Association of N.Y.
- Series I. Education, 1977-2019; 3.75 linear feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials documenting the Garveys teaching, and include organizational newsletters, conference programs, and agendas, meeting notes, and correspondence from various committee meetings. The activities of the American Irish Teachers Association and the Irish American Heritage and Culture Week Committee (a New York City Board of Education initiative) are particularly well represented. These materials focus almost exclusively on organizations and education initiatives devoted to increasing and improving the teaching Irish and Irish American culture and history, such as a proposed curriculum on the Irish Famine/Great Famine.
  Arrangement
  Folders are arranged alphabetically.
  - American Conference of Irish Studies Mid-Atlantic Regional Conference, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Annual Conference, 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Annual Conference, 1994-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Annual Conference, 2005-2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Annual Conference, 2010-2014 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Annual Conference, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Annual Conference, 2018-2019 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Annual Conference Registration Forms, 1994-2016 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Correspondence, 1995-2018 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Installation of Officers, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Irish American Conference Program, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Meeting Notes and Agendas, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Newsletters and Other Collected Documents in Binder, 1988-2003 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Proposal for US Stamp Commemorating 1916 Easter Rising, after 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - American Irish Teachers Association: Things Irish Newsletter Binder, 1986-2018 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Association of Teachers of New York, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Catholic Teachers Association of Brooklyn, 1985-2019 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Committee (Board of Education), 1996-2019 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Committee (Board of Education), 1996-2019 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Poster, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 1998-2016 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Irish American Heritage and Culture Week: Programs, 2017-2018 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Irish American Studies Committee of the United Teachers Federation (UFT), 1977-2016 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Irish American Teachers Association: Newsletters (Tir na n-Og), 2005-2014 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Irish Famine/Great Hunger Curriculum, 1991-2000 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Irish Famine/Great Hunger Curriculum, 1991-2000 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Irish Famine/Great Hunger Memorial (Battery Park, New York City), 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - New York City Department of Education Emerald Society, 1977-2018 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - New York Irish History Roundtable, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Pace University: Ethnic Diversity Conference, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series II. County Mayo, 1950-2019; 4.5 linear feet in 7 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box
  The series documents the Garveys active engagement with various County Mayo-centered social organizations through photographs, newspaper articles, and programs for conventions and other annual events. Materials documenting the activities of the Mayo Society of New York comprise the majority of this series.
  - All-Ireland Fleadh (Ballina), 1997 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - County Mayo Association of Boston: Banquet Programs and Correspondence, 2008-2016 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Mayo Association (Dublin): Yearbook, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Mayo Association of Chicago: Description of Group, after 2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Mayo Association of Philadelphia: Annual Ball Programs, 1996-2010 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Mayo Association of Philadelphia: Annual Ball Programs, 1996-2010 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Mayo Associations World Convention: Programs, 1995-2016 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mayo Men's Patriotic and Benevolent Association of the City of New York: Diamond Jubilee Program, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mayo Men's Patriotic and Benevolent Association of the City of New York: Centennial Programs, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Mayo Men's Patriotic and Benevolent Association of the City of New York: 104th St. Patrick's Ball Program, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Mayo Ladies Auxiliary Organization: Oversize Photograph, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Mayo Ladies Auxiliary, Mayo Men's P.B. and B. Association, and Mayo Football Club: Photograph of 1st Annual Mass and Communion Breakfast, 1950 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Mayo Society of Greater Cleaveland: Annual Ball Programs, 2005-2019 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Mayo Society of Greater Cleaveland: Annual Ball Programs, 2005-2019 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2013 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2014 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2015 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2017 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Annual Ball and Dinner Programs, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Binder of Collected Organizational Documents, 1950-2019 (Box 10, Folder 3-6)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Certificate of Incorporation, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Correspondence, Flyers, Newspaper Articles, 1990-2019 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Man and Woman of the Year, 1996-2019 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Man and Woman of the Year, 1996-2019 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Newsletters, Flyers, Agendas, 1996-2018 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Newspaper Articles, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
  - Mayo Society of New York: Photographs, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - Paul O'Dwyer Human Rights Program at CUNY School of Law: Kick-off Celebration Program, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - West Side Irish American Club: Booklet, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Series III. Irish American Organizations, 1935-2019; 4 linear feet in 6 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box
  The series documents the Garveys engagement with Irish American organizations through photographs, newspaper articles, and programs for conventions and other annual events. The majority of the organizations in this series are in the New York City. The Ancient Order of Hibernians, the United Irish Counties Association of New York, and planning groups for various St. Patrick's Day parades are particularly well represented.
  - An Spreach Gaelach, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Bronx County Board (Division 3), 1997, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: New York County Board (Division 4), 1994-2011 (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: New York County Board (Division 4), 1994-2011 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Rockland County Board, 2015 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians: Queens County Board, 2012 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Brian McGinn Research on Korean War, United Irish Counties Association, and Family History, 2003-2004 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Buttons, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Catholic Daughters of America: Oversize Photograph of Communion Breakfast, 1935 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Conradh na Gaelige (Bronx): Oversize Photograph of 25th Anniversary Dinner and Ceili, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - County Cork B.P. and P. Association of New York: Annual Dinner Journals, 2013-2015 (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
  - County Leitrim Society of New York, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Donegal Association of New York, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Emerald Isle Immigration Center: Annual Dinner Dance Programs, 2006 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Emerald Isle Immigration Center: Annual Dinner Dance Programs, 2012 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Emerald Isle Immigration Center: Correspondence, 1993-2017 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Emerald Isle Immigration Center: Fall Fundraiser, 2015 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York: Annual Banquet Programs, 2011, 2013 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - Ireland Chamber of Commerce (US): Celtic Ball Program, 2014 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Irish American Society of Nassau, Suffolk, and Queens, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Irish American Writers and Artists: Eugene O'Neill Lifetime Achievement Award, 2010, 2014 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Irish Ancestral Research Association (Sudbury, MA), 1995 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Irish Cultural Society (Garden City, NJ), 2004-2019 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Irish Family History Forum: Newsletters, 2017-2019 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Irish Family History Foundation, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Irish Genealogical Society: Newsletter (The Septs), 1991-1998 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - New Haven Gaelic Football and Hurling Club, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters and Ephemera from Multiple Organizations, 2000-2019 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Ohio Irish American News, 2018 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parades: General, 1997-2019 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parades: Brooklyn, 2011-2013 (Box 15, Folder 2-4)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parades: New York City, 2002-2019 (Box 15, Folder 5-9)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parades: New York City, 2002-2019 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parades: Photographs, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - United Irish Counties Association of New York: General, 1998-2018 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - United Irish Counties Association of New York: 1916 Easter Rising Committee, 2014-2016 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - United Irish Counties Association of New York: Annual Banquet Programs, 2012-2015 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - United Irish Counties Association of New York (likely): Contact Sheet, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 16, Folder 10)